<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: work | jtobin.ca]]></title>
  <link href="http://jtobin.ca/blog/categories/work/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jtobin.ca/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-07T23:52:43-02:30</updated>
  <id>http://jtobin.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jared Tobin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notes On Another Guy's Notes]]></title>
    <link href="http://jtobin.ca/blog/2014/03/06/notes-on-high-performance-browser-networking/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-06T18:52:20-03:30</updated>
    <id>http://jtobin.ca/blog/2014/03/06/notes-on-high-performance-browser-networking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently bought Ilya Grigorik’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/High-Performance-Browser-Networking-performance/dp/1449344763">High Performance Browser Networking</a>, which is an excellent book.  Also excellent is that Ilya wrote <a href="http://www.igvita.com/2013/09/29/retrospective-high-performance-browser-networking/">a great retrospective</a> on his book-writing process.  </p>

<p>He made a few noteworthy points about the whole endeavour:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>A ‘shitty first draft’ is the initial goal of most any writing.  Just get to the keyboard and start mashing the keys.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Consistency is key</strong>.  Show up and get to work.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Early feedback is invaluable.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Incremental milestones and deadlines are helpful.  </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Writing is an excellent way to expose the initial sloppiness of one’s thinking.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I think these are all excellent insights, but the second and third ones really stand out to me.</p>

<p>Early and constant feedback is just <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vQyrMMAbXgc">really important</a>.  This is something that I’ve had to constantly remind myself of when working on largely-solo projects.  Having others examine your work immediately gives you an idea of its promise.  Are the other parties excited by it?  Indifferent?  Confused?  Can they point out an area that you haven’t really understood all that well, or something important that you missed?</p>

<p>And above all else, <a href="/blog/2014/01/27/the-unreasonable-effectiveness-of-habit/">consistency is sacrosanct</a>.  This idea is only getting reinforced with time. </p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
