<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: productivity | jtobin.ca]]></title>
  <link href="http://jtobin.ca/blog/categories/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jtobin.ca/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-08T00:09:01-02:30</updated>
  <id>http://jtobin.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jared Tobin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notes On Another Guy's Notes]]></title>
    <link href="http://jtobin.ca/blog/2014/03/06/notes-on-high-performance-browser-networking/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-06T18:52:20-03:30</updated>
    <id>http://jtobin.ca/blog/2014/03/06/notes-on-high-performance-browser-networking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently bought Ilya Grigorik’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/High-Performance-Browser-Networking-performance/dp/1449344763">High Performance Browser Networking</a>, which is an excellent book.  Also excellent is that Ilya wrote <a href="http://www.igvita.com/2013/09/29/retrospective-high-performance-browser-networking/">a great retrospective</a> on his book-writing process.  </p>

<p>He made a few noteworthy points about the whole endeavour:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>A ‘shitty first draft’ is the initial goal of most any writing.  Just get to the keyboard and start mashing the keys.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Consistency is key</strong>.  Show up and get to work.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Early feedback is invaluable.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Incremental milestones and deadlines are helpful.  </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Writing is an excellent way to expose the initial sloppiness of one’s thinking.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I think these are all excellent insights, but the second and third ones really stand out to me.</p>

<p>Early and constant feedback is just <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vQyrMMAbXgc">really important</a>.  This is something that I’ve had to constantly remind myself of when working on largely-solo projects.  Having others examine your work immediately gives you an idea of its promise.  Are the other parties excited by it?  Indifferent?  Confused?  Can they point out an area that you haven’t really understood all that well, or something important that you missed?</p>

<p>And above all else, <a href="/blog/2014/01/27/the-unreasonable-effectiveness-of-habit/">consistency is sacrosanct</a>.  This idea is only getting reinforced with time. </p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Unreasonable Effectiveness of Habit]]></title>
    <link href="http://jtobin.ca/blog/2014/01/27/the-unreasonable-effectiveness-of-habit/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-27T01:11:16-03:30</updated>
    <id>http://jtobin.ca/blog/2014/01/27/the-unreasonable-effectiveness-of-habit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Exactly 41 days ago I started a project called <a href="http://750words.com">750 Words</a>,
which is simply a habit of writing a meagre 750 words every day.  They can be
written on anything; just pick a topic (or several topics) in your head and get
to writing about it.</p>

<p>When I originally started, I thought that this would be a great way to work on
blog posts, research papers, my dissertation, and so on.  Not so much the case,
I’ve found.  After much internal debate as to its merits (the subject of at
least one entry), the best use that I have found far 750 Words thus far has
been a complete mind dump every morning over breakfast.</p>

<p>Initially I tried rigorously picking a topic and writing essays and technical
entries or what have you, but this seemed to actually go against the spirit of
the exercise.  Nowadays I just open the browser and crank out whatever’s on my
mind.  It generally takes me about 15 minutes.</p>

<p>Why do I deem this to be a good use of my time?  More than anything, I think,
it has been by observing the results over time: I’ve sustained a streak now for
37 days straight, and quite enjoy waking up every day and putting another X on
the calendar by virtue of writing another entry.  I don’t want to stop, and
indeed, don’t intend to.  The main reward to me has been  seeing a basic goal
manifest as a string of X’s on a calendar; the little 750-word-minimum mind
dumps (which constitute over 32,000 words now) are a bonus.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I’d often heard about the <a href="http://lifehacker.com/281626/jerry-seinfelds-productivity-secret">‘chain’ method</a>
attributed to Jerry Seinfeld for boosting productivity, but kind of dismissed
it as ‘not a good fit’ for me (whatever that means).  I’ve been productive in
various endeavours by just <em>doing</em> the thing in question - playing musical
instruments, swimming, coding - without feeling I actually needed to resort to
keeping track of a formal chain or what have you.  Slavish devotion to schedule
is a bit foreign to me.  And,
<a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/2013/01/13/write-every-day-is-bad-advice-hacking-the-psychology-of-big-projects/">not everyone recommends it</a>.</p>

<p>When it comes to writing, however, the same approach hasn’t seemed to work.</p>

<p>I’ve always found technical writing to be a difficult task, and have
historically resorted to binging to get the job done.  But, binging on a
tough activity is unpleasant, unpleasant activities breed anxiety, anxiety
breeds procrastination, and procrastination leads to guilt.  The cycle is what
I would call ‘supremely sub-optimal’. </p>

<p>I read a great book about a week ago called <a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Write-Lot-Practical-Productive-ebook/dp/B001Y35G60">How to Write a Lot</a>
which advocates as its primary advice <strong>allotting regular time to write, and
writing during that time</strong>.  In other words, enforcing a habit by slavish
devotion to schedule. </p>

<p>It has now been six days since I started forcing myself to specifically do some
technical writing for at least two hours a day, and marking an X down (using
<a href="http://dontbreakthechain.com">dontbreakthechain.com</a>) when that goal is
completed.  And, seemingly miraculously, much of a dissertation chapter has
materialized from thin air - sans the anxiety, procrastination, and guilt I
normally associate with working on it.</p>

<p>Of course, I’m only six days into this ‘habit’ of mine, so let’s see how long
it lasts in practice.  But, I really can’t imagine it going away: the decrease
in stress and accretion of results I’ve observed in only six days has been
amazing.  If I somehow start finding a two hour commitment too burdensome, I’ll
just knock it back to one hour instead.  And if that winds up being too
strenuous (in which case I probably have bigger problems to worry about) I can
go to thirty minutes or even less.</p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Unreasonable_Effectiveness_of_Mathematics_in_the_Natural_Sciences">Math</a>
and <a href="http://research.google.com/pubs/archive/35179.pdf">data</a> are well-known to be
‘unreasonably effective’ in some sense, but habit just might be as well.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Learning as a Side Project]]></title>
    <link href="http://jtobin.ca/blog/2013/12/19/side-projects/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-19T22:42:02-03:30</updated>
    <id>http://jtobin.ca/blog/2013/12/19/side-projects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I regularly find myself wanting to learn too many things at once.  This might
be justifiable in some sense; there’s an awful lot out there to learn.  Often,
skimming over some topic or other feels like enough to develop a sufficiently
high-level model of what it is or how it works.  Armed with that (dangerously
small amount of) knowledge, however, the urge to pick up some other topic tends
to arise..  and so the process repeats.</p>

<p>This is all well and good in order to survey what’s out there, but left
unchecked, a survey of topics is all one might get.  <em>Le dilettantisme</em> can be
understandable, but never desirable.</p>

<p>Some time ago, I decided to try restricting myself to learning only one
particular topic for two weeks at a time, as a bit of a side project.  Think of
it as a ‘learning sprint’, if you will.  The idea is that the time between
iterations is sufficiently short to ensure that one can’t hunger too badly to
switch to some other topic mid-sprint.  At the same time, each iteration is
lengthy enough to ensure a reasonable amount of immersion and depth.</p>

<p>I managed a single iteration, but due to travel and a lack of conviction about
the whole thing, never started another.  I think I’m going to start again, but
with a little more intent this time.</p>

<p>Two weeks can be a long-as time for some topics, though, so I believe I’ll work
in one-to-two week commitments, depending on the subject.</p>

<p>To start, I’m going to choose <a href="http://zeromq.org/">0MQ</a>, a framework that I
sort-of know and definitely love.  We’ve used it in production on a previous
app I worked on, and I’ve even contributed to the official Ruby bindings.  But,
I still have a lot to learn about it.</p>

<p>So let’s see how it goes.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
