<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: engineering | jtobin.ca]]></title>
  <link href="http://jtobin.ca/blog/categories/engineering/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jtobin.ca/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-07T23:40:14-02:30</updated>
  <id>http://jtobin.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jared Tobin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Synchronous Remote Collaboration]]></title>
    <link href="http://jtobin.ca/blog/2014/06/01/quick-remote-pairing/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-01T04:00:48-02:30</updated>
    <id>http://jtobin.ca/blog/2014/06/01/quick-remote-pairing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don’t really do a ton of pair programming.  By the nature of my work and
geographical location I tend to work i) largely independently ii) on small
teams iii) consisting of people who live about a dozen time zones away from me.</p>

<p>I would <em>like</em> to do more, or at least try it out a bit more.  In the past I’ve
done it very occasionally while trying to pick up something completely new from
an expert, but I think the experience would be more valuable while working on
something familiar but tough, or even just for a change of pace now and then.</p>

<p>In the past I’ve used <a href="http://join.me" title="join.me">join.me</a> for screen sharing plus voice.  I found
it to be lighter-weight and better quality than Skype.  But that already seems
to be a bit old-fashioned nowadays; I’ve since taken to using Hangouts for most
of my calls, and I’d rather be able to work with people more interactively than
screen sharing will allow.</p>

<p>Since servers/instances on your cloud provider of choice are so cheap and easy
to manage these days, I decided to put together a quick pairing environment
using <a href="http://www.vagrantup.com" title="Vagrant">Vagrant</a>, <a href="http://aws.amazon.com" title="AWS CLI">AWS</a>, <a href="http://www.ansible.com/home" title="Ansible">Ansible</a>, and <a href="http://tmux.sourceforge.net/" title="tmux">tmux</a>.  The idea is that
when you’d like to collaborate with someone or other, you just quickly fire up
a cloud instance with all your favourite junk on it, ssh (or mosh) in, and get
right to work in a familiar environment.  Everyone connects to the same tmux
session on an ephemereal cloud instance, which is then just halted or destroyed
as soon as you get bored of each others’ company.</p>

<p>I’ve created a Github repo <a href="https://github.com/jtobin/pair-up" title="pair-up">here</a> that hopefully makes it quite easy to get
this setup going.  Feel free to use that as a base for your own setup if you’d
like to try it for yourself.  It’s even pretty much plug and play so long as
you enjoy vim, tmux, and all of my configuration settings (ps, I re-bind the
tmux prefix to C-s).</p>

<p>TODO: build a custom AMI to dodge the long provisioning waits.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
